Guide to the Stanford University Postcard Collection
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University postcard collection
1891-1990
PC0078
Stanford University
Owens, Justine E., Dr.
1.5 Linear Feet Approximately 1149 items in 5 boxes
Collection depicts Stanford University buildings, grounds, and people; subjects include athletics and athletic facilities, student amusements, the cactus garden, old chemistry building, dormitories, fraternity and sorority houses, views of the Quad and Inner Quad, Lake Lagunita, libraries, Stanford mausoleum, Memorial Arch, Memorial Church, museum, the Palo Alto tree, university workers (primarily images of horse-drawn wagons), David Starr Jordan, Domenico Grosso ("the Stanford hermit"), and the presidential installation of John C. Branner. A number of items depict damage to buildings from the 1906 earthquake. There are also a few items depicting Palo Alto and surrounding communities.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc/university-archives
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Scope and Contents
Collection depicts Stanford University buildings, grounds, and people; subjects include athletics and athletic facilities, student amusements, the cactus garden, old chemistry building, dormitories, fraternity and sorority houses, views of the Quad and Inner Quad, Lake Lagunita, libraries, Stanford mausoleum, Memorial Arch, Memorial Church, museum, the Palo Alto tree, university workers (primarily images of horse-drawn wagons), David Starr Jordan, Domenico Grosso ("the Stanford hermit"), and the presidential installation of John C. Branner. A number of items depict damage to buildings from the 1906 earthquake. There are also a few items depicting Palo Alto and surrounding communities.
Access Terms
Stanford University -- Buildings.; Postcards.; postcards -- California.; Stanford University; Stanford University. Department of Athletics; Branner, John Casper; Owens, Justine E., Dr.; Mitchell, Edward H.; Jordan, David Starr
Collection Contents
- Postcards (individual)
  - Agassiz in concrete, 1906; 1; B/W Print
    Caption: Statue of Agassiz Displaced from Its Pedestal On Library Building, Stanford University
    Imprint: M. Rieder
    pillars and part of arch visible
    Agassiz, Statue of
  - Agassiz in concrete, 1906; 2; Photo
    Imprint: Robinson & Crandall
    front of figure visible; front of quad visible
  - Agassiz in concrete, 1906; 3; B/W Print
    Caption: Statue of L. Agassiz, fell from pedestal above, piercing concrete sidewalk; statue was not hurt; after earthquake of April 18, 1906
    Imprint: Frank Davey & Howell D. Melvin
    image has border and white space
  - Angel of Grief with canopy, 1907 pm; 4; Tinted Print
    Caption: Angel of Grief, Stanford University, Cal.
    Message: "Hello Dode" from "Clarence"
    Imprint: M. Rieder (for C. H. Woerner)
    shows statue, canopy, railing
    Angel of Grief
  - Angel of Grief with canopy, pre 1906; 5; Tinted Print
    Caption: 865 - Angel of Grief, Stanford University, California
    Imprint: Edward H. Mitchell
    same view as no. 4
  - Angel of Grief with canopy, pre 1906; 6; Tinted Print
    Caption: 5083 Angel of Grief, Stanford University, California
  - Angel of Grief without canopy, post 1906; 7; Tinted Print
    Caption: Angel of Grief, Stanford University, California 5390
    Imprint: Pacific Novelty Company
  - Angel of Grief with broken canopy, 1906; 8; Tinted Print
    Caption: 5041 The fallen statue, "The Angel of Grief," Stanford University, California; after the earthquake of April 18, 1906
    Imprint: Cardinell-Vincent Co.
    shows statue, pieces of broken canopy, vase of flowers
  - Angel of Grief with broken canopy, 1906; 9; B/W Print
    Caption: STANFORD UNIVERSITY, PALO ALTO, CALIFORNIA, AFTER EARTHQUAKE. Gleamy white, kneeling low, the Angel of Grief breathes a prayer.
    shows statue, pieces of broken canopy, vase of flowers; image smaller than postcard (i.e. has a border)
  - Angel of Grief with fencing, post 1906; 10; B/W Print
    Caption: The Angel of Grief - Stanford S-574
    statue, iron fence, lawn in front
  - Angel of Grief, post 1906; 11; Tinted Print
  - Angel of Grief, post 1906; 12; Photo
    sepia toned, possible photo
  - Art Gallery exterior, circa 1920; 13; B/W Print
    Caption: reverse: Art Museum, Stanford University, California
    Imprint: Albertype Co., (Hyde's Book Store)
    as viewed from in front of Quad; library visible in background
    Art Gallery
  - Hoover Tower, Quad, & Palm Trees with cyclist done in fabric, circa 1980; 14; Color Print
    Caption: Greetings from Stanford University
    art work by Barbara Mendelsohn
    art work
  - Back of auditorium in Assembly Hall, showing organ, circa 1910; 15; Photo
    pencil note re organ being in Hall for short time while Church was being repaired
    Assembly Hall
  - Back of auditorium in Assembly Hall, showing organ (oblique angle), circa 1910; 16; Photo
  - Female student in red dress holding Stanford banner (sketch), 1907; 17; Color Print
    Caption: 'Rah! 'Rah! 'Rah! 'Rah! 'Rah! 'Rah! 'Rah! 'Rah! Stanford!
    Message: Hope mother will have a pleasant vaction. Love [illegible]
    Imprint: R. Hill, University Series No. 9
    Athletics
  - Stanford football player running with ball (sketch), 1905; 18; Color Print
    Caption: Leland Stanford Junior. Rah Rah Rah-Rah / Rah Rah-Rah / Rah Rah-Rah / Rah-Stanford
    Imprint: Ullman Mfg. Co.
    also had Univ. seal
  - Stanford and Cal football players (sketch), Undated; 19; Color Print
    Caption: Stanford vs U of C
    Message: Tom - The Navy PX finally came thru - my apologies for the long delay LE
    Imprint: Stuart (Palo Alto)
    artwork signed Helmick /09
  - woman in red dress with LS banner (sketch), 1905; 20; Color Print
    Caption: Leland Stanford
    Imprint: Ullman Mfg Co. #1514
    different sketch than no. 17
  - Car decked out for tournament of roses, with six guys and a dog, 1909; 21; Tinted Print
    Caption: Pasadena's Tournament of Roses on New Year's Day
    Imprint: Newman Post Card Co. Art series no. 14
    "Stanford" spelled out in foliage; accompanying note identifies men in car
  - Rugby game with card section in stands showing "S", 1911; 22; Photo
    Caption: written in ink: Nov. 11, 1911
    band and yell leaders also visible
  - California card section at football game, 1911; 23; Photo
    Caption: written in ink: "Stanford - California Nov. 11, 1911 California side"
    Message: These are FootBall views showing opposite side of the Stanford Field. This view is the Berkeley-Calif golden C in a blue [lined?] Bear...
  - Stanford card section ("S") at football game, with balloons rising, 1911; 24
    Caption: written in ink: "Stanford section Nov. 11 - 1911"
    Band and yell leaders also visible
  - "LSJU" spelled out in stands at rugby game, Undated; 25; Photo
  - LSJU spelled out in stands (probably at rugby game), Undated; 26; Photo
    Caption: in ink: "yours truly" with arrow
    Message: Mail time: - Nothing from you yet. Well I may see you in a year or two again even if you dont write. to: Miss Carrie Isabella
  - Stands at athletic event, "S" in white, 1908 pm; 27; Photo
    Message: Just two weeks more, but those two will be merry ones. I have three examinations to look forward to and then for the sunny South for me.
    I didn't send you one of these cards did I. My noble form may be seen just to the right of the x that was a gradn old game, believe me. As ever ATK [?]
    to: Viola Burroughs
  - Rugby game with Stanford rooting section, Undated; 28; Photo
    Message: This is a view of a portion of the field last Saturday. It shows the Stanford rooting section and part of the bleachers on the Stanford side. 23,000 people were present. P.A.R.
    to: Mrs. J. G. Lamont
  - Stanford rooting section, forming letter "S", Undated; 29; Photo
  - Band on sidelines of football game, 1915; 30; Photo
    Caption: in ink: Stanford - Santa Clara game S.F. Nov. 13, 1915
  - Stands at football game with yell leaders, 1912; 31; Photo
    Caption: The Big Stanford-California Rugby Game
    Message: note: Big Game 1912, Nov. 9, 1912. Berkeley. Tie 3 to 3. Taken while singing Hail Stanford Hail / Dorothy & I peaked at this picture on our knees in front of the window on Monday night. I bought this Tuesday night - however.
  - Women fans at football game in stands, Undated; 32; Photo
    Imprint: Robinsons & Crandall
    most fans are women, wearing very large hats - [other views show men fans]
  - Band on field during half time of 1972 Rose Bowl game, 33; Color Print
    Caption: reverse: The Stanford band outlines its unnatural axe at the 1972 Rose Bowl, in a tribute to the traditional symbol of Stanford athletic endeavor. This formation remains one of the few traditional segments of the otherwise contemporary and spirited Leland Stanford Junior University Marching Band shows.
    Imprint: R. and C. Hakanson
  - Rugby players and ball, 1908; 34; B/W Print
    Caption: Rugby Stanford 1908
  - Scoreboard with spectators, S 13, C 8, 1913; 35; Photo
    Message: note: Stanford - California Game / Stanford turf, November 8, 1913
  - Track team with coach, 1912; 36; Photo
    Caption: Stanford Track Squad, 1912
    Message: This is the bunch that is going to do the work tomorrow. I am going to run the 2-mile again and believe me, its going to be a fast one, too! I'll do it or bust. Best wishes George
  - Track team and coach in front of brick building, circa 1911; 37
    Message: Dear Uncle Herman, Received letter and several papers of you and have been trying to get a letter back at you but just now is the beginning of another siege of exams. On reverse of this is a picture of Stanford Track Team just before meet with U. Cal. Will write again next week. Sincerely, George
  - Football (?) team picture, 1910; 38; Photo
    Message: note: The Freshman Team. Oct. 15, 1910. Hall made the only score for Stanford. the score was 3 to 3.
  - Football (rugby?) team picture, 1911 pm; 39; Photo
    Message: [identifies team members]
  - Baseball team picture, 1912; 40; Photo
    Caption: Stanford 1912 Baseball Squad
    Message: These are the boys that will come thru next Sat. even if we did lose to-day. FER. to: L.J. Rehm
  - Football team picture, Undated; 41; Photo
    possibly during 'rugby' years
  - Women's fencing team, circa 1913; 42; Photo
    Message: [identifies individuals]
  - Basketball pavilion, exterior, Undated; 43; Tinted Print
    Caption: Basket ball pavilion, Stanford University, California 6082
    Imprint: Pacific Novelty Co.
    Basketball Pavilion
  - Bonfire structure with students posed on structure, Undated; 44; Photo
    Bonfire
  - Bonfire structure; sign: Get on the boat California, 1911; 45; Photo
    Caption: in ink: Freshman's work Nov. 9, 1911
  - Bonfire structure with camponile, Undated; 46; Photo
  - Bonfire structure, with tombstone "The end of a fruitless mission", 1915; 47; Photo
    date from "tombstone"
  - Bonfire structure, sign "this for you berkeley", 1913; 48; Photo
    Message: note: Stanford - U.C. football game. Freshman Bon-fire November 6, 1913
  - Bonfire structure, with wooden goat on top, 1912; 49; Photo
    Caption: The Big Game Bonfire - Before
    in pencil on front: 1912
  - Bonfire structure, Undated; 50; Photo
    Message: Hows this for a real bonfire, Dad? You can use the telephone post for a yard stick about 20 feet long. That may be Nelson and me by the post. Everything O.K.
    to: C.C. West
  - Bonfire burning, Undated; 51; Photo
  - Bonfire burning, with students watching, Undated; 52; Photo
  - Bonfire burning, Undated; 53; Photo
    Imprint: Bear Photo Co.
  - Bonfire burning, [1911]; 54; Photo
    Message: note: Thursday night - Nov. 9, 1911
    photo shows some oxidative-reductive deterioration
  - Bonfire burning, 1913; 55; Photo
    Message: note: Stanford - U.C. football game. Freshman Bon-fire. November 6, 1913
  - Front of Bookstore with fountain (the claw), 1976 pm; 56; Color Print
    Caption: Stanford University
    Message: [in Spanish]
    Imprint: R. & C. Hakanson
    Bookstore (new)
  - Front of bookstore with fountain (the claw), 1978; 57; Color Print
    Imprint: R & C Hakanson
    different image than no. 56
  - Front of Branner Hall, with automobiles, circa 1920; 58; Tinted Print
    Imprint: Albertype Co.; Palo Alto book Shop
    "hand colored"
    Branner Hall
  - Branner Hall exterior, circa 1920; 59; Color Print
    Caption: Branner Hall, Stanford University, California 6583
  - Business School building, circa 1966; 60; Color Print
    reverse lacks any printing
    Business, Graduate School of
  - Cactus garden path and plants, Undated; 61; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: The cactus garden, Stanford University
    Message: Will answer your letter in about a week. Will let you know how well she enjoy the [?] as soon as she is able. Love to all the babies and wife also self. - Fred & Winnie
    Cactus Garden
  - Cactus garden path and plants, Undated; 62; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: The cactus garden; Stanford University
    same view as no. 61, but one edge is different
  - Man and woman in cactus garden, Undated; 63; Photo
  - People posing in cactus garden, Undated; 64; Photo
  - Man and woman standing next to very large cactus, Undated; 65; Photo
    same woman as in no. 64
  - Path and plants in cactus garden, Undated; 66; Photo
  - Path and plants in cactus garden, Undated; 67; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: No. 42. Cactus Garden, Stanford University, Cal.
    Imprint: Hyde's Book Store
  - Path and plants in cactus garden, 190- pm; 68; Color Print
    Caption: Cactus Garden
    Message: Dear Rubie - This is a view of the cacus gardens near the Mausoleum. ... It's suffocatingly warm here & there isn't a bit of cold water on the place so we have to walk to Palo Alto to get a cold drink. Monday night the Encina boys gave their "night shirt" parade all over the Quad & it surely was funny. [more] to Ruby Durgin from Bel
  - Plants in bloom in cactus garden, circa 1905; 69; Color Print
    Caption: 2173 - In the cactus garden, Stanford University, California
    Imprint: Edw. H. Mitchell
  - Lake Lagunita and dorms (Lagunita Court and Roble), circa 1935; 70; Photo
    Campus, Aerial Views
  - View of Quad from hills side, Hoover Tower on right, circa 1942; 71; Color Print
    Imprint: West in Color Card
  - View of Quad and Palo Alto, 1921; 72; Photo
    in DAYS OF A MAN, V. II, p. 778
  - View of Oval, Quad and hills behind, circa 1922; 73; B/W Print
    Caption: Stanford University Campus from the Air. Crandall's Palo Alto, Calif.
  - View of Oval and Quad, circa 1938; 74; B/W Print
    image very grayed-out
  - View of engineering buildings, Quad, Stadium, circa 1940; 75; B/W Print
  - View from Hoover tower looking along front of Quad, circa 1980; 76; Color Print
  - Wide view of campus, Lake Lagunita, hills, mountains, circa 1970; 77; Color Print
    Imprint: Scenic Art, Inc.
  - SLAC, aerial view, circa 1970; 78; Color Print
    Imprint: Mike Roberts
    pre-printed confirmation of tour reservation
  - View of campus, Lake Lagunita, hills, mountains, circa 1981; 79; Color Print
    Message: Does the East wing have a blue tile roof?! Thanks for your help. Dianne
    Imprint: Smith Novelty Co.
    roof of new Green Library is blue (still under construction)
  - Oval and Palm Drive, circa 1895; 80; Photo
    horse & buggy on Palm Drive
    Campus roads
  - Palm Drive looking toward Quad, post 1906; 81; Sepia Print
    Imprint: Albertype Co.; Hyde's Book Store
    Arch appears to be gone
  - Lasuen near site of 1905 library, post 1906; 82; Photo
    Caption: verso: The Automobile Road, Stanford University
    dome from 1905 library still standing; car on the road
  - Palm Drive, circa 1900; 83; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: No. 54 University Avenue, Stanford University, Cal.
  - Palm Drive, with horse-drawn carriages, circa 1895; 84; Photo
  - Road on outskirts of campus (?), Undated; 85; Photo
    Caption: verso: The Road to the Bridge; Stanford University
  - Palm Drive, Undated; 86; B/W Print
    Caption: verso: Approach to campus. Stanford University, Cal.
    Imprint: Albertype co.; Hyde's Book Store
  - Palm Drive, Undated; 87; Sepia Print
    Caption: On the Avenue, Stanford
    shows mostly an intersection with Palm Drive; seat built around tree is visible
  - Salvatierra, Undated; 88; Color Print
    Caption: Salvatierra Row, Stanford University, Cal.
    Imprint: Newman Post Card Co.
    shows street, trees, sidewalks - no houses visible
  - Oak trees and path (Arboretum ?), Undated; 89; Color Print
    Caption: Stanford oaks, Stanford University, California
    Campus, Scenic Views
  - Oak trees and path (Arboretum ?), Undated; 90; B/W Print
    Caption: 5079 Stanford oaks, Stanford University, California
    Imprint: Edward H. Mitchell for H. W. Simkins
    same image as no. 89
  - Flowers in bloom somewhere on campus, Undated; 91; Color Print
    Caption: Poppy Field, The Campus, Stanford University, California 6577
    Message: Having a swell time here in Almaden. Go out quite a lot. Regards from "Dee"
  - Viewing spot in the hills overlooking campus, circa 1905; 92; Sepia Print
    shows bench with umbrella-type roof; buildings in background appear to be musuem & 1905 gymnasium
  - Two people sitting on a stone wall, Undated; 93; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: Queeners. Stanford University
    remnant of Coutts stone wall??
  - Bridge over San Francisquito Creek, Undated; 94; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: The Foot Bridge, Stanford University, Cal.
  - Bridge over San Francisquito Creek, Undated; 95; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: The Foot-bridge Stanford University
  - Governor's Lane, Undated; 96; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: Eucalyptus Avenue, Stanford University
  - Palm Trees, Undated; 97; Photo
    noted on back: Stock Farm - Grounds
  - Walk from Encina to the Quad, 1915 pm; 98; Photo
    Message: [Christmas greetings to Jeanne Hitchcock]
    identified in ink on back as "walk from encina to the quad"
  - Path in Arboretum (?), Undated; 99; Sepia Print
  - Path in Arboretum (?), Undated; 100; Sepia Print
  - Arboretum or possibly Stanford home grounds, 1910 pm; 101; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: No. 12. Stanford oaks, Stanford University, Cal.
    Message: Rec'd word from my sister and cousin that if weather was fine they would be down Sunday so I can't stay with you, altho' I shall have to go to San Jose to have a suit fitted.... My Penmanship girl has rec'd permission from her parents to drop penmanship (the pupils please themselves at this private school) so I am to have something else to do....H. Dixon to Ruby Durgin
  - Governor's Lane, Undated; 102; Sepia Print
  - Path along Palm Drive, Undated; 103; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: The Avenue to Stanford University
  - Governor's Lane, Undated; 104; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: Eucalyptus Avenue, Stanford University, Cal.
    Imprint: Albertype Co; Hyde's Book Store
  - Near the boat house, circa 1910; 105; Photo
    in ink on verso: The old style at the Boat house about 1910-1915
  - Tree full of woodpecker holes, Undated; 106; Sepia Print
  - Tree full of woodpecker holes, close-up view, Undated; 107; Sepia Print
  - Cedro Cottage, with palm tree, Undated; 108; Sepia Print
    Caption: verso: Cedro Cottage, Stanford University, Cal.
    Cedro Cottage
  - Chapel and '95 oak, 1908 pm; 109; Tinted Print
    Caption: '95 Oak and Old Chapel, Stanford University, Cal.
    Chapel
  - Chapel and '95 oak, Undated; 110; B/W Print
    Caption: '95 Oak and Old Chapel, Stanford, Cal.
    Imprint: [missing]
    same image as #109
  - Chapel and '95 oak, 1909 pm; 111; B/W Print
    Caption: University Chapel and 95 Oak. Stanford University Palo Alto, California
    Message: I got your postal and was glad you was going to have a dance for me. To show you my heart is on the right side I will dance for you tonight. Oh - are you going to Frisco for [?] week if so I may see you... to Miss Mable Enos
    same image as #109 but a little more at the edges is included
  - Chapel and '95 oak, Undated; 112; Tinted Print
    Caption: 95 Oak and Old Chapel, Stanford University
  - Chapel interior view, Undated; 113; Photo
    Chapel (Interior)
  - Old Chemistry, exterior, side view, post 1906; 114; Sepia Print
    Chemistry (Old)
  - Old Chemistry from front of Quad, pre 1906; 115; B/W Print
  - Old Chemistry, front view, post 1906; 116; Sepia Print
  - Old Chemistry, front view, oblique, post 1906; 117; B/W Print
    Imprint: Albertype; Hyde's Book Store
  - Old Chemistry, front view, oblique, post 1906; 118; Sepia Print
    same image as No. 117
  - Old Chemistry, exterior view, with museum on right, post 1906; 119; Sepia Print
    stone fence in front of quad with vases also visible
  - Old Chemistry, exterior view, with museum on right, post 1906; 120; Sepia Print
    vantage point is closer than in no. 119
  - Old Chemistry and Museum thru Quad Arches, post 1906; 121; Sepia Print
    Caption: 1900 Chemistry Building and Museum Stanford University, California
  - Old Chemistry and Museum thru Quad Arches, post 1906; 122; B/W Print
    same image as no. 121
  - Old Chemistry and Museum thru Quad Arches, post 1906; 123; Color Print
  - Old Chemistry from front of Quad, post 1906; 124; Sepia Print
    Quad front steps and one lamp visible
  - Old Chemistry and front steps of Quad, pre 1906; 125; Color Print
    Caption: Chemistry Building, Stanford University, California
  - Old Chemistry and Museum, pre 1906; 126; Color Print
    Caption: 5215 chemistry Bldg. and Museum Stanford University
    Front steps of Quad and lamp visible
  - Old Chemistry exterior view (from Museum side), post 1906; 127; Sepia Print
  - Old Chemistry and Museum, pre 1906; 128; Color Print
    Caption: 187 Chemistry Building and Museum, Stanford University, California
    Imprint: Charles Weidner, photographer
    oval with flowered edge visible
  - Old Chemistry and Museum, pre 1906; 129; B/W Print
    Caption: Chemistry Building, Stanford University, Cal.
    lamp and ornate piece on front of quad visible
  - Old Chemistry, pre 1906; 130; Tinted Print
    Caption: 418 - Chemistry Building, Stanford University, California
    Imprint: E. P. Charlton & Co.
    same view as #129, but less of museum visible
  - Old Chemistry, pre 1906; 131; Sepia Print
    Caption: 5074 - Chemistry Building, Stanford University, Californa
    same view as #129 but Museum not visible
  - Old Chemistry, exterior, post 1906; 132; B/W Print
    Caption: 1905 - chemistry Building, Stanford University, California
  - Old Chemistry, exterior, post 1906; 133; Sepia Print
    same image as #132
  - Crothers Hall, oblique aerial view, 134; Photo
    Imprint: Photo Post Card
    first wing only
    Crothers Hall
  - Crothers Hall, oblique aerial view, 135; Photo
    shows both wings as well as Wilbur Hall in the background
  - Dinkelspiel Auditorium, front view, 1965; 136; Color Print
    Imprint: Rudolf Meyer
    Dinkelspiel Auditorium
  - Dinkelspiel Auditorium, front view, 1965; 137; Color Print
    as seen from upper level of Old Union
  - Eating Clubs, exterior, 138; Photo
    Caption: Dining Clubs, Stanford Univ., Cal.
    Eating Clubs
  - Eating Clubs, interior courtyard, 139; Photo
    Message: Friday morning. Just leaving. Got your letter last evening. It is a beautiful warm clear quiet day. P.A.R. O.R. R.R. to Mrs. Lamont
  - Eating Clubs, interior courtyard, 1917 pm; 140; Sepia Print
    Caption: Dining Clubs, Stanford University, California